比较当世人们的生活
When we compare the present life of man on earth.
和那些已无从考据的时代
with that time of which we have no knowledge,
我觉得就像一只小小麻雀
it seems to me like the swift flight.
在某个冬日 飞过宴会大厅的那一瞬
of a single sparrow through a banqueting hall on a winter's day.
在那片刻的绚丽后
After a few moments of comfort,
便消失在自己曾出现过的冬日景致中
he vanishes from sight into the wintry world from which he came.
每个人只在这个世界上 出现那短短的一瞬
Even so, man appears on earth for a little while,
这短短一瞬前后的故事
but of what went before this life or what will follow,
我们都不得而知
we know nothing.
最近
In these last days.
关于失去 我想了很多
I have been thinking a great deal about loss.
大人 一个人失去了什么
What loss, Your Grace,
是最无法挽回的
is to man the most irrecoverable?
他的德行
His virtue.
不是
No.
通过行动 他可以重拾德操
For by his actions, he may redeem his virtue.
那他的荣誉
Then his honor.
不是
No.
同样的 总有办法可以挽回
For again, he may find the means to recover it,
如同他可以重获他失去的财产一样
even as a man recovers some fortune he has lost.
那我就想不到了 陛下
Then I cannot say, Your Majesty.
是时间 大人
Time, Your Grace.
所有我们失去的东西里
Of all losses,
时间是最无可挽回的
time is the most irrecuperable,
因为我们不能回到过去
for it can never be redeemed.
（王后凯瑟琳·帕尔的逮捕令）
沃尔特
Walter!
小心保管这份文件
Take this very carefully.
并送交给李斯里大人
and give it to my Lord Risley.
是 大人
Yes, Your Grace.
法国最高上将大人到
The Lord High Admiral of France.
陛下
Your Majesty.
您好 大人 法兰西的贵宾
Salutationes Domine, Praefectus Magnus Galliae.
谨此代表吾父亨利八世 欢迎您的光临
Salvete Regis Enrici octavi maiestatis.
谢谢 殿下
Thank you, Your Highness.
能拜访贵国是我至高的荣耀
It is my great privilege and honor to be here.
上将大人
My Lord Admiral.
夫人
Madame.
请允许我引荐两位公主 玛丽小姐
May I present His Majesty's daughters…the Lady Mary.
伊莉莎白小姐
and the Lady Elizabeth.
幸会
Enchant?.
没想到可以受到陛下家人 如此热诚的接待
I never thought to be welcomed in this cordial way by His Majesty's family.
你是我们的贵客啊 德尼波上将
Ah, but you are a very special and honored guest, Admiral D'Annibault.
另外您的造访也正合时机
And your visit most timely.
我想陛下应该快到了
I am sure His Majesty will be here presently.
赫德福德大人似乎深得陛下信任
My Lord Hertford seems to be in the King's good graces.
恐怕正是如此
I fear it seems to be so.
伯爵势力正日涨夜窜
The Earl grows more powerful daily.
全因陛下体弱而他又控制着储君
because of the King's infirmity and his control of the boy.
陛下驾崩后愿上帝助我
God help us then if the King should die.
但愿
Yes.
不过我也有耳闻
But I have heard many say.
不少人士更希望您登基为女王
that the people would rather see you anointed as Queen.
而不是把国家交给
than leave the country at the mercy.
一个孩子和他自负的舅舅
of a mere child and an overweening uncle.
那王后又将如何
And what of the Queen?
啊…
Ah…
您很快… 能听到相关政论
you shall hear more on that subject…very soon.
国王驾到
The King!
陛下
Your Majesty.
上将
Admiral.
我们很欣慰能和法国签订新协定
We are very pleased to make a new treaty with France.
我和德皇之间将不再有任何联系
I will have no further business with the Emperor…
他曾多次背叛我
who has betrayed me at every turn.
我向您保证我们将是您忠实的伙伴…
I can assure Your Majesty that you will find us good and faithful friends…
绝不会像德皇那样
unlike the Emperor.
你应该有所耳闻 在我国
As you know, in my kingdom.
已进行了不少宗教改革
I have made many changes to religious life.
我重塑了曾经腐败堕落的教堂
I have reformed a corrupt church.
我驱除了数百年来的
I have swept aside hundreds of years.
谎言和迷信
of lies and superstitions.
我向各族人民揭露了
I have revealed to all mankind.
教皇并非上帝的使者
that the Pope is but a fallible prince,
而不过是会犯错的凡人
and not the voice of God.
这些无疑你都应该听过
All this, no doubt, you'll have heard.
我当然知道陛下
I am certainly aware that Your Majesty.
在您的国家实施了很多变革
has wrought many changes-in your own kingdom.
那如果我们要联盟 先生
Well, if we are going to be allies, Monsieur,
那我建议一个更深远的变革
then I propose a further change.
我建议在两国境内
I propose that Mass.
全部废除弥撒
be abolished in both our realms…
由一种简单的圣餐礼来代替
and replaced with a simple communion service.
你觉得如何
Now, how would you feel about that?
陛下 我没有权力重议协定条款
Your Majesty, I have no authority to renegotiate the terms of our treaty…
陛下也知道 尤其是在吾王病危之时
especially, as Your Majesty knows, my King is dying.
梅毒 我知道
Of syphilis, I know.
我很遗憾
I am very sorry to hear it.
我认识弗朗西斯很久了
I have known Francis a long time,
请务必转告我的慰问
and I beg you to send him my love.
你也一并告诉他
But you may also tell him.
他的疾病即意味着他的凡人之身
that his disease is a reminder of his own mortality!
时过境迁 他恐怕已经忘了
Which, in times past, he has forgotten!
沃尔特？
Walter?
我有东西要给王后看
I have something for you to show the Queen.
我应该要交给李斯里大人的
I'm supposed to take it to Lord Risley.
藏好了 王后看完后还给我
Hide it. When the Queen's read it, give it back to me.
好俊呢
so handsome.
哦 妹妹 别说了
Oh, hush, sister.
什么事
What is it?
哦 我的上帝
Oh my God.
怎么回事
What is that?
谁在嚎呢
Who is it?
是… 是王后陛下 陛下
It's… it's the Queen's Majesty, Your Majesty.
那她为什么嚎成这样
And why is she screaming like that?
我去看看她
I'll go and see her.
凯特
Kate.
这是怎么了
what is it?
我…
I…
我怕…
I fear…
你对我有所不满
you have grown displeased with me.
何出此言
Why so?
因为…
Because…
我怕你已经彻底抛弃我了
I fear that you have… utterly forsaken me.
我不明白
I don't understand.
什么事让你有此顾虑
What has caused you to think so?
有什么原因会让我对你不满意吗
Why would I have reason to be displeased with you?
你没有对我不满吗
Are you not displeased with me?
凯特
Kate,
我再问你一次
I will ask you one more time:
有什么原因会让我不满吗
Is there any reason I should be?
没有
No.
完全没有 陛下
There is none, your Majesty.
日安 夫人
Good day, my Lady.
妹妹 夫人们
Sister! Ladies!
现在你们都要按我说的做
Now, you must do as I ask.
销毁所有私藏的书籍
Clear your coffers of all books…
无论你觉得它们是不是禁书
whether you suppose them to be forbidden or not!
从今往后 无论如何 我们的谈话将不再涉及
From now on we shall talk no more, amongst ourselves,
任何宗教或有争议的议题
of any matters, whether religious or controversial,
我也将竭尽所能
and I shall try, in all things,
来迎合国王的心意
to conform myself to the King's mind.
快行动 快啊
Now go. Hurry!
- 赫德福德大人 - 小姐
- My Lord Hertford. - Mademoiselle.
日安
good day.
我能见公爵吗
May I be presented to His Grace?
很不巧 大人 公爵身体欠安
Alas, my Lord, His Grace is indisposed.
他身感风寒 现在还卧床不起
He caught a chill and is still abed.
我很遗憾
I am very sorry to hear it.
等公爵身体好了 我再来拜访
I will return some other time, when the Duke is well.
不 不 大人
No, no, my Lord.
见你我还撑得住
I am well enough to see you.
怎么可以呢
Que fais-tu?
不用担心 亲爱的 我没事
Ne t'inqui?te pas, ma Cherie. Je vais bien.
大人请
My Lord.
我以为你那派现在正和加德纳主教派
I think your faction is engaged in a fight to the death.
斗得你死我活
with Bishop Gardiner and his.
我不会对您有所隐瞒 大人
I will not hide the truth from you, Your Grace.
国王身体羸弱
The King's infirmity.
我侄儿尚且年幼
and the youth of my nephew.
这使得继位问题如箭在弦
make the question of succession urgent.
赌注已博到了极限
The stakes could not possibly be higher.
我没猜错的话 你想要知道
And you desire to know, I assume,
我站在谁那边
on which side of the argument I belong?
大人 无论您是否在意
Your Grace, whether you will it or not,
您对国王的影响可谓举足轻重
you carry a great weight of confidence and influence with the King.
这点大家都了解
And everyone knows that.
但是很少有人知道您的妻子 公爵夫人
But fewer people know that your wife, the Duchess,
同我的妻子 安 加上王后
and my wife Anne, together with the Queen,
在宗教信仰上可谓亲密无间
are as close on matters of religion as it is possible to be.
这种亲密关系让我有勇气
And this close affinity has emboldened me,
在此时此刻同您敞开心扉
now, to approach Your Grace.
相信您妻子有告诉您 公爵夫人同我已形同路人
Surely your wife has told you that the Duchess and I are estranged!
她的好恶已与我无关
Thus her affinities are not necessarily my own.
而你却强加在我身上
and you do me a disservice to assume they are.
大人 请原谅我…
your Grace, forgive me…
我原谅你
I do forgive you.
我甚至原谅你把傲慢可怜的萨里
I forgive you even for hounding poor,
逼到绝路上
proud Surrey to his death…
总归那是他咎由自取
for it was his fault.
但是说到宗教信仰
But as to religion.
我从来没读过福音书 也不打算读
I have never read the Gospels-and never shall.
我相信福音书给你带来了启示
I am sure they enlighten you,
但对我而言 我宁愿它们保持神秘
but I prefer them to remain mysterious.
至于承诺中更好的世界
And, as for the promise of a better world,
我只能说英格兰曾经是那么美好
I can only say that England was merry before,
更广义来说
and all things considered,
我希望一切都能回到从前的样子
I would all things were as they used to be in times past.
大人 如果我得不到您的支持
Your Grace, if I do not have your support…
我可否请教您是否会抵制我
may I ask if you will act against me?
我不知道这能算不算给你的答案 赫德福德大人
I'm not sure if this is any answer, my Lord Hertford.
我很崇尚法国农夫的一句名言
But I have always been drawn to a phrase used by the French peasants:
「感谢上帝赐予的一切」
"Praise the God of all,
「喝杯酒」
"drink the wine,
「让一切顺其自然」
"and let the world be the world."
赫德福德夫人到 大人
Lady Hertford, Your Grace.
赫德福德夫人
My Lady Hertford.
大人
Your Grace,
我不知为何被传召至此
I was summoned here but I have no idea why.
有什么能帮你的吗
I wonder how I may help you?
夫人 告诉我实情 就是对我最大的帮助
You may help me, my Lady, by telling me the truth.
我知道 你是最近
You were a friend, I believe,
被施火刑的异教徒
of the heretic Anne Askew,
安·阿斯科的朋友
recently burned?
我的确与她相识
I was acquainted with her.
我想不只是相识吧
You were more than acquainted, I think.
她在狱期间 你的一个仆人…
While she was a prisoner one of your servants…
一个穿蓝色外套的人
a man wearing a blue coat…
向她提供过钱财
gave her money.
我希望她不会太受罪
I desired to make her circumstances more tolerable.
这只是作为教徒的慈悲
I was only acting out of Christian charity.
我听说有人非法刑讯逼供
I had been informed that those who tortured her,
把她绑在架子上拉扯
illegally, had stretched her on the rack.
直到四肢筋肉坏死
until the strings of her arms and legs were perished.
但你承认她是公开的异教徒
But you admit she was a self-confessed heretic?
因此你同她有染本身就够定罪了
You are therefore guilty by association.
你有逮捕令吗
You have a warrant for my arrest?
你不会用这张逮捕令的
You will never serve that warrant.
有何不可
Why not?
因为我知道你的秘密
Because I know your secret.
什么秘密 赫德福德夫人
What secret, my Lady Hertford?
你装得像个圣人
You are not such a saint as you appe…
其实不然 对不对 大人
are you, Your Grace?
你并没有放弃世俗的物质追求吧
You have not exactly renounced worldly goods…
是吗
have you?
康沃尔郡有两座修道院
There are two monasteries in Cornwall.
在陛下的命令下被问抄 关闭 烧毁
They were stripped and closed, on His Majesty's orders, and burnt.
可事实上他们根本没被问抄亦或烧毁
Except that they were neither stripped nor burnt,
其财产都被秘密转移到了大人名下
but their titles and contents were quietly transferred to Your Grace.
你是很富有
Thus you are a rich man indeed…
但都是从国王那里偷来的
but only by embezzling from the King.
我建议你撕了这张逮捕令
I advise you to tear up your warrant,
大人
Your Grace.
陛下 王后陛下到
Majesty, Her Majesty the Queen.
凯特 到这儿来
Kate. Come in here.
陛下
Your Majesty.
很高兴你能来
I am glad you have come.
你能替我解开一些疑惑
You can resolve me of certain doubts.
凯特 我在想你能从福音书
I wonder, Kate, how much you think you can learn.
和其他宗教书籍中学到多少
from reading the Gospels and other religious books?
陛下
Majesty,
既然上帝已任命您 作为我们的最高领袖
since God has appointed you as Supreme Head of us all,
我将从您那里获悉上帝的旨意
it is from you that I will ever learn.
啊 但事实并非如此啊
Ah, but that surely is not so!
你已经是学者了 凯特
You have become a doctor, Kate,
我们已经见识过好多次了 你已经在指导我们了
to instruct us-as we have seen many times before…
不需要被我们指导了
but not to be instructed or directed by us!
陛下 我想您误会我的意图了
Majesty, I think my meaning has been mistaken.
我一直认为女人来指导 她的夫君是多么荒谬
for I have always held it preposterous for a woman to instruct her Lord.
即便如此
And yet,
有时候你的宗教观念同我们大相径庭
you seem sometimes to have a different view of religion than we do.
所以我需要您的指正
Only so that you could correct me!
原谅我 陛下
Forgive me, Your Majesty,
我原以为谈话和讨论
but I thought that talking and discussing.
可以为您驱散疾病带来的病痛和苦闷
helped to ease the pain and weariness of your present infirmity.
我的大胆进言
And it encouraged me in my boldness,
也是极度渴望
in the hope of profiting.
从您那里获取真理的结果
from your learned discourse.
我 我只是一个女人
I am, I am but a woman,
女性的柔弱
with all the imperfections natural.
导致了诸多天生的缺陷
to the weakness of my sex…
因此
and therefore,
任何疑惑
in all matters of doubt and difficulty.
我都会以陛下的判断
I must refer myself.
为最终指导
to Your Majesty's better judgment,
您是我的主人和领袖
as my Lord and head.
确实如此吗 亲爱的
Is that so, sweetheart?
所以你的主张实则好意
And you made your argument for no worse ends?
那我们可以和好如初了
Then we are perfect friends again.
多谢恩典 陛下
I thank Your Majesty.
我保证
I promise.
我不会再对你有所怀疑
that I will never doubt you again.
亲爱的凯特
Sweet Kate.
陛下
Majesty.
陛下 需要我废除明天
Majesty, shall I rescind Your Majesty's order.
逮捕王后的命令吗
to arrest the Queen tomorrow?
为何
Why?
音乐
Music.
怎么了 亲爱的
What is it, sweetheart?
没什么
Nothing.
我做梦了
I was dreaming.
梦到我们在布洛涅的时候…
We were back in Boulogne…
我把你放走了
but I let you go.
我在这里
I'm here.
- 黎明了吗 - 还没有呢
- Has the dawn come yet? - Not yet. Not yet.
我讨厌夜晚
I hate the nights.
会让人以为是永恒的黑暗
They make you think of perpetual night.
嘘 亲爱的
Hush, darling.
黎明即将到来 你也会好起来的
The dawn will be here soon, and you well again.
- 布里奇特… - 我在 亲爱的
- Brigitte… - Yes, my darling?
我非常幸福
I'm so happy.
凯特… ？
Kate…?
怎么回事
What is this…?
大法官 所为何事
Lord Chancellor! Why have you come?
我来执行王后的逮捕令
I have come to execute the warrant for the Queen's arrest.
并将夫人送往伦敦塔
and to escort her, and her Ladies, to the Tower.
你个混蛋
You knave!
你个彻头彻尾的混蛋
You arrant knave!
滚 别让我看见你
Get out! Get out of my sight!
- 陛下 原谅我… - 滚
- Your Majesty, forgive me. - GET OUT!
也把你的跟屁虫给带走
And take your bastards with you.
我… 我很遗憾
I… I am sorry.
很遗憾大法官会
?? the Lord Chavcellor should.
犯这样的错误
make such a mistake.
他完全不值得你同情
You don't how little he deserves your sympathy.
他不是你的朋友 凯特
He was not your friend Kate.
- 赫德福德大人 - 赫德福德大人
- Lord Hertford! - My Lord Hertford!
大人 我已经解释了
Your Grace, I have already explained,
他骂我是混蛋 火气冲天
he called me a knave! All manner of things.
可是他是骂给谁听的呢
But for whose ears?
可能他是想警告王后 她还未能宽心放肆
Supposing he still wants the Queen to feel falsely secure?
就算他是装生气 我觉得那也是冲着我来的
If it was feigned anger, it seemed very real to me!
诸位大人 国王缺席
My Lords, in the King'sbsence,
议会依然在此聚集以表决是否赞成
Council is called upon to declare its content.
同法国的和平协议条款
with the terms of the peace treaty with France.
- 赞成请说「是」 - 是
- All in favour say "aye" - Aye.
议会还需要讨论 关于王位继承人
Council is also called upon to discuss all arrangements made.
爱德华王子殿下
for the security and safety of His Highness Prince Edward,
安全事宜的诸项安排
heir to the throne,
以及他继承俗权
and all provisions made for his temporal.
和神权的各项条件
and spiritual welfare.
大人们 请问
My Lords, pray,
出于何种目的导致 您现在提出这样的议题
what induces you to discuss such things now,
如上涉及的条件已毫无疑问
when all such provisions are already made.
王子按照陛下的命令 在温莎也安然无恙
and the Prince is secure at Windsor, by His Majesty's orders?
- 是啊 - 的确
- Aye. - true.
赫德福德大人
My Lord Hertford,
议会依然有义务确认以上事宜…
Council is still constituted to examine such matters…
尤其正当国王疾病缠身
especially since the King's infirmities.
我们更有必要防范于未然
give us all cause to think of the future.
大法官大人 预示国王身故
And it is treason, my Lord Chancellor,
- 乃叛国行为 - 是
- to envisage the King's death! - Aye!
大人 这不是为了王子着想嘛
My Lord, all our concern is for the Prince.
你为了王子
Your concern?!
你忘记了他是我的血亲吗
Are you forgetting that he is of my blood?
他也是国王的血脉
He is also of the King's blood,
这让我们有足够的理由来确保 照顾王子的人和事都安全妥当
which gives us cause enough to examine those put in charge of him.
恰恰我们发现 这些人当中
And among them, some of whom we find,
比如他的老师 就可能是异教徒
like his tutors, to be suspected heretics!
你凭什么叫嚣异教 你
You talk of heresy! You!
你是什么东西 不过是 依仗着教皇狐假虎威的走狗
And what are you but a puffed-up porkling of the Pope's?
大人
My Lord!
我依然要说 赫德福德大人
I still say…My Lord Hertford…
你对王子和王位
that the real truth behind your intentions.
真正的野心
towards the Prince and the crown.
一定高于你对国王的忠诚
must be placed before the King.
- 你干了什么？ - 把手拿开
- What are you doing? - Take your hands off!
陛下
Your Majesty,
加德纳主教请求面见陛下
Bishop Gardiner desires an audience with your Majesty.
拒绝
Refused.
这位大人天性爱惹是生非
His Grace has a troublesome nature.
我不想在这里再看到他
and I don't want to see him here ever again.
请他离开宫廷
I desire him to leave my court.
遵命 陛下
Yes, Your Majesty.
大人 陛下命令您离开宫廷
Your Grace, His Majesty instructs you to leave court.
- 赫德福德大人 - 赫德福德大人
- My Lord Hertford. - Lord Hertford.
赫德福德大人
My Lord Hertford.
大法官大人 有何赐教
Lord Chancellor. What may I do for you?
如果你接受 我恳请你原谅
You may forgive me, if you find it possible to do so,
我过去交友不慎 现在万分悔恨
from some past associations, which I now regret.
我愿意全心全意忠于
I have no hesitation in pledging my utter loyalty.
大人的阵营
to Your Lordship's house,
将来我亦将如效力于陛下一样
and I trust in future I can serve you.
为你尽犬马之劳
as faithfully as I have always served His Majesty.
真是万分荣幸 大法官大人
I am most grateful to you, my Lord Chancellor.
陛下
Your Majesty…
霍尔拜因大师到
Mr. Holbein.
- 霍尔拜因大师 - 陛下
- Mr. Holbein. - Majesty.
我有个任务交给你
I have a commission for you.
我很荣幸 陛下
I am most grateful to Your Majesty.
我想陛下指的是肖像
I assume Your Majesty means a portrait?
你为我父亲著过肖像
You once painted my father.
现在你来替我画
Now you will paint me.
我深感荣耀
I am deeply honored.
亲爱的
Sweetheart,
sweetheart…
陛下有口谕
here is a messenger from His Majesty.
大人
Your Grace,
陛下听闻您身体不适
His Majesty has heard of your indisposition.
他要见您
and has asked to see you.
不行
No!
这不可能 你去问问医生
That is impossible. Ask the physicians.
那我该如何向陛下回禀呢
What shall I tell His Majesty?
告诉他…
Tell him…
我去
I shall come.
可能你不能去啊
But you can't!
亲爱的 英格兰国王召唤我
How can I lie in bed, my love,
我怎么能躺在床上置之不理呢
when the King of England has summoned me?
让他们帮帮我
Just get them to help me.
你来这干吗
What are you doing here?
我来看我的女儿
I have come to see my daughter.
这让你吃惊了吗 亨利
Why should that surprise you, Henry?
你并没有善待她
You have not always been kind to her.
看到她孤苦无依
I have wept so often.
被自己的父亲抛弃
to see her alone,
我常常泣不成声
abandoned by her father.
你就是为了这个回来的吗 凯瑟琳
Is that why you've come back, Katherine,
为莫须有的事指责我
to chide me for all that I am not?
她早该成婚为人妻了
She ought to be a long time married by now.
也早该为人母了
She ought to have her own children.
走开 幽灵
Go away, shade.
走开 凯瑟琳
Go away, Katherine.
以前你就抛下了我
You sent me away before…
但我依然爱你
though I loved you.
在上帝眼中 从前我就一直是你的妻子
But I was still your wife in God's eyes.
现在依然还是
And still am.
萨福克公爵到
His Grace the Duke of Suffolk.
查尔斯
Charles.
陛下
Majesty.
他们说你病了
They told me you were ill.
所以我必须见你
So I had to see you.
我只是有点发烧
I have a slight fever.
陛下请不要靠太近
Perhaps Your Majesty should not come so close.
我们相识已久
We've known each other a long time,
很久了
a very long time.
是的
Yes.
往事历历在目
And I remember everything.
事实上 记忆中
In fact, I remember.
很久以前的事
things from long ago.
比昨日之事 更加鲜活如新
better than I remember yesterday.
我忘不了陛下的妹妹
I remember Your Majesty's sister so well.
还有陛下赐封我公爵之时
And when Your Majesty made me a Duke…
只有上帝明白
God knows why!
你是我在约克
You were my general,
和法国的大将军
in York and in France,
因为我只信任你
because I could trust no one else.
现在 查尔斯 我要你
And I beg you now Charles,
相信我一次
to trust me.
我有力量让你恢复健康
I have the power to make you well again.
你知道的
You know that.
他们说你快要死了…
They told me you were like to die…
但你不会死的
but you won't die.
我不允许
I forbid it!
跪下
Kneel.
上帝在上
By the grace of God,
我 亨利八世
I, the Eighth Henry…
英格兰 爱尔兰 法兰西国王
King of England, Ireland, and France…
真理及英格兰教会的捍卫者
Defender of the Faith and of the Church of England.
命令你痊愈
command you to be healed!
- 萨福克公爵夫人 - 夫人
- My Lady Suffolk. - My Lady.
夫人
Your Grace.
请允许我代表大人 所有忠实的奴仆和同僚
May I say, on behalf of all His Grace's loyal servants and staff,
在这样悲恸的日子里 我们同夫人您一样
that we are as heart-broken and wretched.
万分遗憾 悲痛欲绝
as Your Grace must be on this unhappy day.
我们深爱着大人
For we all loved His Grace.
同夫人您 作为他妻子 和他的儿子并无不同
as much as you, his wife, and son, loved him.
多谢
Thank you.
您的慰问和忠诚 让我和犬子深受感动
Your sympathy and loyalty touch my son and I most deeply.
夫人
Madame.
安息吧
Requiescant in pace Domini.
愿永恒之光普照于你
Et Lux perpetua luceat eis.
安息吧
Requiescant in pace.
把他葬在温莎的圣乔治教堂
He is to be buried at St George's Chapel at Windsor.
费用由我承担
At my expense.
是 陛下
Majesty.
我来告诉你 赫德福德大人
I tell you this, my Lord Hertford:
在查尔斯·布兰顿替我效力期间
As long as Charles Brandon served me,
他从未背叛过一个朋友
he never betrayed a friend,
也从未对敌人采取不光彩的手段
nor ever… took unfair advantage of an enemy.
我担保 在我的宫廷里 没有其他人可以做到
Which is more than I can say for anyone else at my court!
我从来没想过他会离开我
I never thought he would die.
赫德福德大人 我们应该讨论一下
We should talk, my Lord Hertford,
我死后该如何妥善安排
about the arrangements for the Prince's minority…
年幼的王子
after I am dead!
陛下 霍尔拜因大师到
Your Majesty, Mr. Holbein is here.
霍尔拜因大师
Mr. Holbein.
陛下
Majesty,
请您允许我向您展示肖像画的进程
with your permission, I came to show you my work in progress.
霍尔拜因大师
Master Holbein.
你为我父亲画肖像时
When you painted my father,
你把他画得
you made his likeness.
年老 体衰
when he was old, sickly, and ill.
他完全不像英格兰国王
He looked nothing like a King of England,
更像个可怜虫
more like a poor wretch!
一个虚弱平庸的将死之人
A feeble, plain, and dying man.
现在你又要在我身上重蹈覆辙
And now you have done the same for me!
陛下 我…
Majesty, I…
霍尔拜因大师 这幅肖像是个谎言
Mr. HOLBEIN! This portrait is a lie!
重画
Do it again!
给我出去
And get out.
你来这干吗
Why are you here?
来看我女儿
To see my daughter.
她是我生命中唯一的圣洁
She was the only pure thing in my life.
但我生时缺忽略了她
And in my life I neglected her,
就因为她只是女儿身 我多想给你生个王子
since she was only a girl, and I wanted so much to give you a son.
但现在我是如此为她骄傲
But now I am so proud of her.
非常骄傲 她很聪慧
Fiercely proud! She is so clever.
虽然在很多方面 她很像我
And though she is like me in so many ways,
却不像我那么恃才而骄
she is not intemperate as I was.
你也为她骄傲吧 亨利
You must be proud of her too, Henry.
是的
I am.
我也替她骄傲
I am very proud of her.
我也知道她非常聪明
And I know how clever she is.
我希望我能再多爱她一点
And I wish that I could love her more.
但是时不时得
But from time to time.
她会让我想起你
she reminds me of you.
还有你的所作所为
and of what you did to me.
我什么都没做过
I did nothing to you.
我是无辜的
I was innocent.
所有对我的指控都是假的
All the accusations against me were false.
我以为你知道的
I thought you knew.
可怜的凯瑟琳·霍华德
Poor Katherine Howard.
她躺在冰冷的地下 就我在身边
She lies in the cold ground next to me.
可怜的孩子
Poor child.
那也不是她的错
It was not her fault either.
但是我们就像两只飞蛾 不顾一切地扑向烈火…
But we were like two moths, drawn to the flame…
燃成灰烬
and burned.
安 不要
Anne, please don't!
国王陛下驾到
His Majesty, the King.
陛下
Your Majesty.
玛丽公主…
Lady Mary…
伊丽莎白公主
Lady Elizabeth…
凯特
Kate…
到这儿来
Come here!
我已经决定
I have decided.
送你们去格林威治
to send you away to Greenwich.
今年我不会和你们一起过圣诞节…
I will not spend Christmastide with you this year…
之后也不会
or thereafter.
- 您何出此言 陛下 - 凯特
- Why, Your Majesty? - Kate,
不要质疑我的决定
do not question my command.
就这样决定了
It is as it is.
是 陛下
Yes, Your Majesty.
玛丽
Mary.
你要负担起当你弟弟慈母的责任
You must be a kind and loving mother to your brother,
我走后
who I leave in this world.
他将成为孤苦无依的孩子
a helpless little child.
父亲 我求您
Please, father, I beg you,
别让我那么快成为孤儿
do not leave me an orphan so soon!
玛丽
Mary,
Mary.
伊丽莎白
Elizabeth.
你还是那么年轻
You are so very young,
但你也要照顾好你的弟弟
but you, too can look after your brother.
是的 陛下 我保证
Yes, Your Majesty. I promise.
愿主保佑你 孩子
Bless you, child.
保佑你
Bless you.
凯特
Kate.
是时候说永别了
The time has come for us to bid farewell.
这是上帝的意愿
It is God's will.
我死后
When I die,
我要求这些先生们
I order these gentlemen.
要如我在世时那样尊敬你
to treat you as if I were living still.
如果你有意改嫁
And if it is your pleasure to remarry,
在你有生之年 我会留给你
I order that you shall have 7, 000 pounds a year.
每年七千英镑的花费
as long as you live for your service,
你可以留着所有的珠宝和首饰
as well as your jewels and ornaments.
走吧
Now go.
我儿还好吗
How is my son?
简
Jane!
他很好
He is well.
我把他照顾得很好
???
亲爱的简
sweet Jane.
他很快会成为国王
And soon, he will be King.
我可怜的儿
My poor boy.
可怜的孩子
My poor child.
不
No!
他是最受宠爱的一个
He is the most beloved.
他是我最重要的儿子
He is my special boy.
他将在花季之年早逝
He will die young.
不会的 不会的
No! No!
可怜的孩子 你对他期望太高
Poor child…you expected too much of him!
他只是个孩子
He was only a boy!
即使是君王也是血肉之躯
Kings, too, are made of clay!
你怎么可以把他隔离在世界之外
And God forbid you locked him away from the world,
就像你父亲对你那样
like your father did with you.
不是的
No!
你还不明白吗
Don't you understand?
你已经扼杀了他
You have killed him!
不是的
No!
诸位臣工 以下将是我的遗诏
Herewith, my Lords, is my testament.
我死后
When I am dead,
在爱德华王子成年前
my Lord Hertford will act as Lord Protector.
赫德福德大人将为护国公
during Prince Edward's minority.
并由大法官李斯立
He will be supported by my Lord Chancellor Risley.
和大主教克兰麦辅佐
and Archbishop Cranmer.
我遗愿
It is my desire.
将我埋在温莎
to be buried next to the body.
我此生挚爱
of my true and loving wife,
简·西摩尔王后身边
Queen Jane Seymour, at Windsor.
建一个体面的祠堂
You shall raise an honorable tomb,
要有我们的肖像
upon which will be our effigies,
音容笑貌要栩栩如生 好似我们只是在沉睡
fashioned as if we are sweetly sleeping.
陛下
Majesty.
Your Majesty.
霍尔拜因大师在礼拜堂等您
Mr. Holbein awaits you in the Chapel.
霍尔拜因大师
Master Holbein,
画得很好
it is well done.
亨利八世卒于1547年1月28日
Henry VII died on January 28, 1547.
他唯一的嫡出王子在九岁时 登基为爱德华六世
His sole legitimate son became King Edward VI at the age of nine.
六年后因病去世
Only to die of illness six years later.
国王的长女玛丽公主
An attempt was made to prevent the King's eldest daughter, Princess Mary,
因其天主教信仰 继位一度受到阻挠
from becoming Queen because of her Catholic beliefs.
最终在1533年登基为女王 她的统治短暂而血腥
She was crowned in 1533. Her Reign was short and turbulent.
她焚烧了很多新教徒殉道者 史称「血腥玛丽」
She burned many protestant martyrs, and became known as "Bloody Mary".
她同父异母的妹妹伊丽莎白 于1588年继位 史称「童女女王」
Her half-sister, Elizabeth, succeeded her in 1558.
伊丽莎白统治英格兰长达44年之久
Known to history as the Virgin Queen, Elizabeth ruled England for forty-four years.
她统治时期被称为「黄金时代」
Her Reign was called "The Golden Age".
亨利八世和伊丽莎白一世
In Henry VIII and Elizabeth I,
都铎王朝诞生了两位 英国史上最著名的君主 《都铎王朝》全剧终
the Tudor dynasty produced the two most famous monarchs in English history.